[Chants]
Within our Nation,
the Mohawk Nation,
there was
no language word for art.
We called it beauty.
It was a way of life.
It was how we lived day to day,
and the path,
the path of beauty.
Cowboy Smithx.
Good to see you.
Good to see you again.
I am glad you made it.
Yeah, well,
I am really happy
just to be here
on your land, you know.
I have heard that before.
[Laughter]
Elder in the Making is kind
of a road trip story, actually,
between a Chinese Canadian (me)
and Cowboy Smithx,
as we go learning about
our shared history and our home.
What started off as
kind of a small exploration
grew into a huge exploration
of Indigenous culture
and history
in Southern Alberta,
on the traditional
territories of Blackfoot.
Actually, you know,
shoot the beautiful landscapes
that exist out there
and understand what they mean
to the people of the land.
I can't even say it was
so close to home; it is home.
What is it that you would want
to tell us, the public servants,
on how we should be building
better relationships
with Indigenous peoples?
Making a genuine
connection with individuals,
specifically elders.
You know, they carry the most
knowledge in our communities.
It is really
a conversation about efforts.
I mean, you have
got to go beyond what is
in your policy here,
at the School.
I mean, you have got
to make it a personal journey
and not one that is part of
the institution you represent.
You can't expect anything.
You can't think there is
a certain level you are going
to get to if you spend
four years with an elder.
It doesn't work that way.
Here is a dangerous conversation
about pan-Indianism.
We are not all the same.
We all have different
circumstances and connections
because the land itself,
the physical geography,
the geology, expresses itself
in different ways.
Definitely, you have
to go above and beyond
what siloed expectations you
may have which may be connoted
to your work or connoted
to some sort of obligation.
Even tokenism is always
kind of a dangerous thing
to get involved with.
Definitely make it genuine,
make it authentic,
if you are going
to connect to somebody.
Know your history.
It is important to know
what you are actually saying
before you say it.
Be considerate, right?
So, when I hear things like,
'Well, we will let
the First Nations do
their dance at the beginning,
or we will let them...',
I mean, come on,
we are done being let in.
I mean, we are foreigners
in our own territory enough that
we don't need to be let anywhere
within our own territories.
So, when it comes
to the language of any type
of circumstance,
it is important to be
very aware
of what you are saying.
Inclusion is a form
of othering and it is...
You know,
I am saying to be respectful.
We are seeing all these types of
stories like Elder in the Making
and like the
Truth and Reconciliation Report,
which I recommend
everybody read.
These all help to start shaping
people's understanding
of how we came to where we are.
[Music]
It is essentially a love story.
It is about Annie,
who is a young, Indigenous girl
who is not
in touch with her culture.
She meets Gordon, who is
a survivor, and he teaches her
about the Indians
residential schools story.
I felt it was timely, and I felt
that art can bring about change.
I want to make people aware.
Truth brings reconciliation;
reconciliation, I think,
can bring harmony;
and harmony
can bring prosperity.
Reconciliation is a word I have
only started using recently.
The fact that we are
even having this conversation
is quite inspiring.
Hopeful is definitely
a part of that,
but we have
been hopeful for too long.
It is time to really take
agency over these conversations
and bring them into fruition.
We are not going to come
and say, 'Oh, it is time
to come to Mohawk lands'.
You know,
we are not going to do that.
It is not our place.
It is your place
to come and ask,
and it is in the asking
you will grow,
learn.
But more importantly,
love for ourselves and others.
[Chants]