If we go back
to the time of contact
and Europeans
coming over to the Americas,
there has always
been this idea of
(and again, it is referred
to as the imaginary Indian)
the Indian that
was created by the Europeans
when they
came over to the Americas.
Part of that imagery, which
later turned into stereotypes,
part of that imaginary
Indian was the idea
that Indians were all the same.
This universal idea
that there is a one.
So, everybody from North
to Central to South America
who was there at the time
got one term: Indian.
There has always been a push
from that very first contact to
try to find a term, one umbrella
term, that describes all,
which has led to
incredible layers of complexity.
It requires a depth
of understanding, but history...
Again, that is like trying
to say, 'Well, if they were
all one, then I guess everybody
from England to Japan was one.'
They say, 'That is incredible.
Everybody was different and
there were thousands of nations,
languages and cultures.'
Well, yes.
It was true here too.
So the quest has always been
to find a singular term,
a singular umbrella term,
that describes all as one.
In the early 1950s,
it was Native.
Well, first it was Indian.
Then it was Native.
In the constitutional talks
it became Aboriginal.
Then there is status
and non-status.
And treaty.
First Nation.
So that search
for the latest umbrella term
is Indigenous.
Indigenous meaning
that we are still searching for
that one term that describes
all, but they will never fit.
We have that sort of
juxtaposition against there is
no one-size-fits-all,
and we always try to find
one size that fits all.
So the struggle to find
that one all-encompassing term
will probably continue.
The counter-trend to that
is to identify people
by their nations.
So whether you are Anishinaabe,
Haudenosaunee, Omgohomi,
however you want to do it,
the correct terminology,
from my perspective,
is to identify and to greet
or acknowledge people from
the nation that they come from,
as opposed to try to find
one term that describes all.
We have always tried
to shoehorn a very large piece
of information
into one particular...
Square peg, round hole.
It has never worked.
It probably never will work.
It doesn't mean
we stop that search.
But I said the more correct
terminology from my perspective
is one that acknowledges
the nation or the people
that they come from.
That usually
keeps you on safer territory.
A lot of people
asked me this question
after the
new government came in.
What is Indigenous, and is that
the appropriate term now?
People want to
be correct and so on.
I explained that it doesn't
necessarily include the Inuit
and other groups and so on.
So, when I introduce myself,
I identify myself as Algonquin.
I am a member
of the Algonquin Nation.
That is how I choose
to introduce myself,
but I don't put a lot of thought
or much care, actually,
into whatever I am described as.
First Nation,
Indigenous, Indian, status,
all of the above...
I have been called
all of the above.
What I suggested to people
who got really wrapped up
in this is to not err
too much into that because,
quite frankly, at the community
level, this is not a big deal.
It is a big deal
for those who want to be
overly politically-correct,
and I think recently
Indigenous has exemplified
the importance of the U.N. DRIP,
the international relationship
that we have promoted
on the world stage.
So it has its time,
but who knows 20 years from now
what we will be called?
[Laughter]